Status: Postdoctoral Researcher, ETH Zürich

Field: Metabolomics, Mass Spectrometry, Natural Products Languages: French (C2), English (C1), German (C1), Italian (C1) Zürich, Switzerland email: adriano.rutz@ik.me website: https://adafede.github.io

Bio

Adriano Rutz is a pharmaceutical scientist with a focus on metabolomics, natural products, and analytical chemistry. He gained industry experience at Tradall SA (Bacardi Group) before completing his PhD in phytochemistry from the University of Geneva. Currently a postdoctoral researcher at ETH Zurich, he develops computational tools and mass spectrometry-based methods to study the chemistry of living organisms. He is committed to open science and open data, and is one of the authors of the LOTUS initiative, which explores new ways of sharing knowledge in natural products research.

Experience

Postdoctoral Researcher, ETH Zürich (2022 - present)

Computational metabolomics at the Institute of Molecular Systems Biology.

Research and Teaching Assistant, UNIGE (2017 - 2022)

Development of LC-HRMS/MS based approaches for comprehensive composition assessment of complex plant extracts. In depth annotation using Spectral Networking.

Plant metabolomics.

Teaching activities with Bachelor and Master students.

Maintenance and optimization of analytical instruments (LC).

Junior Research Chemist, Tradall (2016 - 2017)

Working in analytical research and Research and Development laboratories following ISO norms.

New products development, analytical and sensory characterization.

In depth analysis of impact compounds, compounds evolution understanding.

Maintenance and optimization of analytical instruments (GC).

Assistant Pharmacist, Pharmacie de la Terrassière (2015 - 2016)

Internship in the frame of Master's degree.

Education

PhD in Pharmaceutical Sciences, UNIGE (2017 - 2022)

Thesis entitled Integrative Analytical and Computational Strategies for Qualitative and Semi-quantitative Plant Metabolome Characterization

B.Sc. and M.Sc. in Pharmaceutical Sciences, UNIGE (2011 - 2016)

Mention excellent for Master's thesis GC chiral separation of main enantiomeric compounds as a tool of Quality Control of some botanicals and related specific final product

Awards

Swiss National ORD Prize (2023)

Awarded for the LOTUS initiative. See more at https://akademien-schweiz.ch/en/medien/press-releases/2023/adriano-rutz-gewinnt-ersten-schweizer-ord-preis/.

Dr Willmar-Schwabe-Young-Talent-Prize (2023)

Awarded for the LOTUS initiative.

See more at https://ga-online.org/dr-willmar-schwabe-young-talent-prize-2023-for-adriano-rutz/.

Sports

Artistic gymnastics trainer, Ecole de Gymnastique Artistique Genève (2009 - 2022)

Artistic gymnastics trainer, with kids from 5 to 12 years

Federal recognition "Moniteur Jeunesse+Sport" (re-assessed each 2 years)

Artistic gymnastics judge, Schweizerischer Turnverband (2009 - present)

Federal recognition "Juge national N3" (re-assessed each 2 years)

website: https://adafede.github.io * email: adriano.rutz@ik.me